A Finding Aid to the Dwinell Grant Papers, 1930-1988, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Dwinell Grant papers
1930-1988
Archives of American Art
Grant, Dwinell, 1912-1991
AAA.grandwin
Archival Resource Key
0.8 Linear feet
The Dwinell Grant papers measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1988. The papers document Grant's career as a painter and filmmaker through awards and certificates, interviews, resumes, and other biographical material; correspondence with friends, colleagues, and art institutions; manuscripts and other writings; business records with Olympia Gallery and Martin Diamond Fine Arts and Graham Gallery; and brochures, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material.
Scope and Contents
The Dwinell Grant papers measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1988. The papers document Grant's career as a painter and filmmaker through awards and certificates, interviews, resumes, and other biographical material; correspondence with friends, colleagues, and art institutions; manuscripts and other writings; business records with Olympia Gallery and Martin Diamond Fine Arts and Graham Gallery; and brochures, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material.
Biographical material includes awards and certificates, resumes, a timeline of Grant's life, some autobiographical notes by Grant and two videotapes PROFILE OF DWINELL GRANT from "Profiles in Excellence" conducted by Gary Perdue, and an interview with Grant for ART BEAT. Correspondence is composed of letters to and from Grant with friends, colleagues, and art institutions. Writings include essays Grant wrote for academic courses and typescript writings expressing Grant's thoughts on art and religion. Business records include Grant's dealings with Martin Diamond Fine Arts and Graham Gallery and the Olympia Gallery during the late 1970s and 1980s. Materials include such things as invoices, appraisals, and storage of artwork. Printed material includes press releases, clippings, programs for plays produced at Wittenberg College, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and brochures and fliers concerning Grant's medical and other filmmaking projects.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection and material lent for microfilming is available on 35mm microfilm reels 4152-4155 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Biographical / Historical
Dwinell Grant (1912-1991) was a painter and filmmaker in Pennsylvania. Grant was born and raised in Ohio. He received early art training from his grandfather, Paul E. Henking, and also studied at the Dayton Art Institute and the National Academy of Design. In 1935, he began teaching at Wittenberg College in Ohio. He was primarily influenced by his association with Hilla Rebay and the Museum of Non-Objective Art (the Guggenheim), and from 1944-1948 worked on an unfinished film project for the Guggenheim. In 1947, he began producing medical teaching films and supplemented his income with work on medical books, while continuing to work on his paintings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the archives by Dwinell Grant in 1988. Additional material was lent for microfilming by Dwinell Grant in 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1940-1988 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1930-1988 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1948 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1978-1988 (0.1 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1936-1988 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Separated Materials
Also found at the Archives of American Art are materials lent for microfilming (reels 4154-4155) including writings, mostly from the 1980s, expressing Grant's thoughts and philosophies concerning himself and his art work, sometimes presented in the format of a journal; one album containing photographs of Grant, his family and friends, and nine albums of photographs of works and of gallery installations, annotated with information on sales, experiments with light, including a formula for stereoscopic drawing, notes on abstractfilms, medical illustrations, and dream fantasies; and two sketchbooks containing abstract drawings. Lent materials were returned to Grant and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Interviews; Video recordings; Filmmakers -- Pennsylvania; Painters -- Pennsylvania
- Biographical Material, 1940-1988; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes awards and certificates, resumes, a timeline of Grant's life, some autobiographical notes by Grant and two videotapes PROFILE OF DWINELL GRANT from "Profiles in Excellence" conducted by Gary Perdue, and an interview with Grant for ART BEAT.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1940-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview Transcript, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    An interview with Dwinell Grant. May possibly be a partial transcript of the video interview for "Art Beat."
  - Interview with Dwinell Grant, 1988 March; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 1)
  - "Profile: Dwinell Grant" from Profiles in Excellence, 1980; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 2)
  - Resumes, 1940-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Timeline, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1930-1988; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is composed of letters to and from Grant with friends, colleagues, and art institutions.
  - Correspondence, 1930-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Writings, circa 1948; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Writings include essays Grant wrote for academic courses and typescript writings expressing Grant's thoughts on art and religion.
  - "Art and Human Need", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Color and the Consumer" by Jean O. Grant, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "The Dynamic Pattern", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Part I: The Process Concept", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The Place of Abstract Design in the Art of Western Europe", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Prologue", 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "The Structure of the Theme", circa 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Twentieth Century Need", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Personal Business Records, 1978-1988; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Business records include Grant's dealings with Martin Diamond Fine Arts and Graham Gallery and the Olympia Gallery during the late 1970s and 1980s. Materials include such things as invoices, appraisals, and storage of artwork.
  - Martin Diamond Fine Arts and Graham Gallery, 1979-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Olympia Gallery, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
- Printed Material, 1936-1988; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material includes press releases, clippings, programs for plays produced at Wittenberg College, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and brochures and fliers concerning Grant's medical and other filmmaking projects.
  - Clippings, 1936-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Medical Projects Brochures, 1973-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Press Releases, 1963-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Wittenberg College, 1936-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1954-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)